hello and welcome
it is
March 2nd 2023 and we're here in octave
live stream 52.1
welcome to the active Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference this is a
recorded and an archived live stream so
please provide us feedback so we can
improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about getting involved in
learning groups and projects such as
live streams
all right
we are in 52.1
and our goal today is to
learn and discuss this awesome paper
geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adoptive
agents of Barb and Acosta at all and
we're gonna just jump right in thanks a
lot Lance for joining and uh
those who have listened to 52.0 will
know me
I'm a researcher and a learner with
respect to this topic so thanks again
for joining and it'll be great to have
you introduce yourself and also tell a
little bit
of the story of how this paper came to
be
sure thanks Daniel for organizing I mean
this is really great and I'm very happy
to be here
um so my name is Lance De Costa uh some
of you may know me I'm a PhD student
both at Imperial College of London and
UCL
I'm mostly working on active inference
than the 300 principle
also some probabilistic machine learning
and today we're going to be discussing
geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adaptive
agents
so how this paper came to be where I
happened to to you know know people in
who do more like statistics machine
learning and so on and
we've always been talking about the
similarities and differences between
what we do in active inference and what
they do and you know sampling
optimization which are uh kind of the
workhorses of statistics and machine
learning and at some point we had a
paper invitation for the Hamburg Coast
statistics and we decided to you know
team up and and make a review article to
see how all these fields uh are that
come from very different uh places
scientifically that have very different
contributors as well and we wanted to
know how they're interconnected and also
how they can help each other
um because we realized for all this time
that we're actually doing similar things
but the communities are very different
they're not very much talking to each
other and I think a main barrier is a
difference in language difference in
jargon so that's that was kind of an
issue when we when we started and so I
wanted to with that all I mean as much
as possible in a paper and see how how
these different approaches to you know
statistics whether it is sampling
optimization inference or decision
making how they can benefit from each
other and how they relate to each other
and and so long story short we're we're
gonna delve into this into more detail
but long story short
um if you want to assemble from a
distribution you can also view that as
an optimization problem
uh so optimization is kind of a you can
see it as the root of sampling and you
want to optimize sampling makes sampling
as efficient as possible
inference you can also see it as an
optimization of beliefs optimization of
probability distribution so it's also an
optimization procedure
and if you want to do decision making
which is what we do in active inference
and reinforcement learning and oh many
different places well do decision making
you actually need optimization and
inference and if you want to do decision
making efficiently you often are going
to need sampling as well so decision
making and active inference is kind of
like what comes at the very end and
requires all of the sophisticated
Machinery of sampling inference
amortization in order to work
so this was really the idea of the paper
um
how does optimization come about how do
you do efficient optimization and of
course there's many different ways to do
that so we decided to focus on natural
ways and and we'll get to that but one
way to do optimization that is very
natural is through techniques from
geometry
um and so same with sampling in sampling
and inference you have geometry that
just comes out very naturally when you
when you want to solve these problems
and so decision making puts it all
together
so that was really the idea of of the
paper can we put all these fields
together and have like a you know like a
connecting line which is based on
Geometry and so that's what we did
awesome great overview so
so many places to
um jump in
I barely even know where to sample from
this distribution let's just start with
sampling though so
what is sampling and how is it being
used how has it been used
and uh
let's characterize sampling and then
move on to these other fields
right well sampling I mean the idea of
sampling is very simple and it's also a
very difficult thing to do so first
explain the idea
the idea is let's say you have a
gaussian in one dimension so it has a
very easy to picture
sampling would be
um so for example
the the gaussian I just mentioned
describes the temperature in the room
though
um in my room it's maybe currently 18
degrees Celsius plus or minus some
variance representing my uncertainty
now
um sampling from the distribution would
be
saying it is maybe 19 degrees or maybe
17 degrees you know drawing a lot of
different temperatures so that if you
put them all together as a histogram
with like their frequency
for example
if you if you ask me what temperature it
is in my room I would say
there's a higher chance that I say 18
degrees so I would say more often if you
ask me this question many times and you
know if you put my answers if you
collect all my answers in a histogram
for example I'd say 18 degrees more
often so that bar around 80 degrees
would be higher and the other
temperatures will be slightly lower and
if you aggregate that you would get a
gaussian get the gasoline which started
with so stumbling in in other words and
very simply it's like drawing a data
point or an observation from an
underlying probability distribution
so you have a distribution let's say a
gaussian that represents your
most likely value of what the
temperature in the room is and some
uncertainty and you just want to draw
one or several observations
uh from that distribution
and you want to draw these observations
so as to preserve the overall statistics
of the distribution that you started
with
so that if you draw infinitely many data
points or infinitely many observations
from the distribution then you can
recover the original distribution so
that's what we want to do
and so why is this useful in the first
place well it just happens all the time
in the things that you want to compute
integrals
um
it just happens all the time so if you
want to for example if you have a
Bayesian inference problem
you have
You Know You observe some data in in the
world it could be Medical Data it could
be it could really be anything and you
have a prior and a likelihood of
observing that data so these are the two
terms in like Bayes rule then you want
to know
um then if you apply base rule you get a
posterior belief about what caused that
data that you observed so for example
um
a practical use case would be some
medical data of a patient that's sick
and you want to know so you get for
example
um you know it's blood pressure
collection of symptoms and so on so
that's your data and you want to know
um what kind of disease or what kind of
a malfunction cause that data so let's
say typically you would have a model of
if I get this if I have this malfunction
of this disease I would have these
symptoms if I have this other disease I
would get these are the symptoms and so
base rule
enables you to infer in the best way
possible
[Music]
the disease that caused the symptoms
that you just saw
so this is like a common thing I mean
something that people use every day in
statistics all the time and arguably
everybody uses is it every day because
like the kind of the thesis of the 300
principle or the result that provides is
that you can describe
um
describe perception in of humans as
doing Bayesian inference so this
inference is a very
uh ubiquitous thing you can describe it
to you can use it to describe perception
uh in humans and you can also use it to
do statistics and solve all kinds of
problems so coming back to sampling
um actually doing Bayesian inference you
have this problem of you know how do you
compute the posterior distribution in
the first place
and it turns out that this distribution
is generally intractable
because you have
um kind of a term in the denominator
that's very hard to compute
and so one way is to compute it is to
use what's called Monte Carlo methods
and Monte Carlo methods are based on
sampling
so long story short in order to do basic
inference you need to compute
uh this like log likelihood term which
is a high dimensional integral
and my way to do it is by using Monte
Carlo methods and Monte Carlo methods
are based on sampling so the sampling
enables you to approximate the high
dimensional integral that you started
with
so now many listeners or or both the
readers of this work will wonder well I
um one thing that people do in the 300
principle and also like kind of like the
the resident of the PNG principle is
you're actually not going to compute
this denominator that's very expensive
to the Bayesian inference but you're
gonna approximate the posterior by
minimizing free energy
which is called variational inference
that's another method of doing Bayesian
inference
and it has many advantages over sampling
sampling also has advantages with
respect to variational inference we can
get into that
um but if you so if if that's what
you're thinking well this is not
necessarily
interesting because we can do
variational inference there's so many
other places where we need sampling in
statistics
um I would say
basically anytime you need to compute an
integral and integrals are all over the
place
um but I think the Bayesian inference
motivation is a nice one because it just
speaks to all of us
um
so how does so so how does actually
sampling getting to the picture of
integration let's say we have an
integral that we need to compute
um an integral is basically let's say
you have a
State space so to be very simple let's
say the state space is my desk so it
would be like a planar surface and we
have a function that's defined on the
desk so this would be like a landscape
over the desk right
um like a 2d 2D surface landscape that's
could be rugged or whatever the integral
of this function is going to be the
volume between the landscape and the
desk
um
so so this is kind of like the geometric
picture of what an integral is
um so this turns out to be very hard to
you know compete in practice because you
have like um let's say you have a very
rough surface and it's not clear how to
you know compute all this volume which
is very irregular
what sampling does
it's gonna pick a few locations on the
desk
um as many as you wish
so let's start by one and it's going to
compute the height
um the the height on under the function
and then
pick another location and compute that
height as well since sampling is gonna
pick locations on the desk at random
and from there it's going to build a
histogram
um that's going to approximate
the the surface that you started with
and so a histogram is very simple
because you get a whole bunch of
skyscrapers if you wish that approximate
this the surface that we started with
and Computing the volume of skyscrapers
is very simple because you know they're
like um
they're like squares you just
um it's like depth times height times
width it's very simple to compute the
volume of those things
um so this is kind of the idea we want
to compute the volume under a rock
surface and to do that we're going to
pick arbitrary locations on the
um yeah on on the desk on the on the
page space and build and at those
locations uh build like skyscrapers at
the height of the surface so you get
like um
a Skyline a histogram that approximates
your original function and it's very
simple to know the volume of the
histogram the volume of the skyline and
so from then
you get an estimate of the integral that
you started with
um so that's kind of like the geometric
picture the beauty of this is that it
works in arbitrary dimensions
and it doesn't suffer from the curse of
dimensionality so this is why it's so
powerful
um if you if you want to know so that
there's a formula that tells you
um how well the volume of your Skyline
will approximate the volume of the
volume that you initially wanted to
compute the integral
so this is
this difference between the integral and
your estimate
um
basically decreases as a function of the
number of skyscrapers that you put in
the more skyscrapers the more precise to
get
and um
and this this bound
um this bound on the error that you have
on your on the on your integral that you
started with it doesn't depend on the
dimension
so
as the the higher dimension on your
state space so let's say let's imagine I
had a higher high dimensional desk
which is very hard to imagine and I had
a function on top of it and I wanted to
compute the area under the function
the higher if my desk was very high
dimensional this would be
the higher than I mentioned the harder
it would be to you know so solve this
problem numerically but with sampling
um actually the the degree of accuracy
that you get through the sampling would
be agnostic to the dimension
says this is why it's so so powerful and
and you just used all the time in
statistics and machine learning when you
imagine you know practical problems that
you have in machine learning going back
to Medical Data uh you could get a whole
bunch of
data about a patient which could be you
know heart rate over time
blood oxygen levels blood glucose levels
body temperature and whatnot there's so
many
data modalities that you would have so
your state space would have many many
dimensions
um and also the the state space of the
different diseases that could have given
rise to
um to all these all these symptoms would
be also very high so it could be it
could be that the patient has you know
fever or it could be
that it has flu I know fever is a
symptom it could be that the disease is
flu it could be that the disease is
tuberculosis it could be a disease it is
AIDS you know there's so many different
conditions or problems that one might
want to you know examine
um so in this particular case of medical
data and this is just like a very uh
simple use case I would say
you have a very high dimensional State
space
and to debase an inference you you have
a very high dimensional integral to
estimate and so when we to do that
efficiently or
I wouldn't maybe efficiently is
disingenuous because it's just very hard
I mean it's just very computationally
intensive to do these things but one way
to do this that's you know state of the
art is through sampling just by drawing
different points at random on this safe
base
and approximating the the the function
landscape and approximating the integral
like that
um so yeah this is really the
uh why this is so important
awesome
so
we've made a sample
where does these topics of accepting or
rejecting a move amongst samples or
discretizing how do we pick that next
sample and then what does it mean to
accept or reject that sample
that's a great question this is
basically like the the heart of sampling
you know uh so if you if you knew how to
do that in full generality
sampling would be solved
um which it isn't so so I'm gonna
tell you a bit like where where things
stand
um
so
the yeah to so to do sampling you need
to pick places at random and you need to
pick places random so as to preserve a
probability distribution so going back
to the example of the desk you want to
pick
um in in the case in that case you want
to pick
samples uniformly on the desk
um if we come back to the previous
example of like a gaussian distribution
you want to pick samples
um
you know that that preserve the gaussian
distribution so you want to preserve it
to take a lot of samples around the mean
a very few samples on the tails
um so it turns out that for those
very simple distributions like uniform
distribution gaussian distribution
um there are ways to sample that do not
require
that do not require what what this paper
is is talking about
so there are ways to sample you know
exactly that that do not lead to any
kind of error and that are very fast
so for gaussians and uniform and a bunch
of other distributions from the
exponential family
you have ways to sample exactly
so the problem is these distributions
they they're not there all the time and
it turns out that very often
you don't have these kind of very simple
distributions otherwise we would be done
so one one simple example uh coming back
to Bayesian inference is the idea of
Jeffries prior so Jeffries prior
is um
is the idea that you should take the
highest entropy prior that's consistent
with the what you know about the system
so
um why why entropy Maxim maximizing so
we know that entropy is a measure of the
uncertainty present in the distribution
and so what Jeffrey what Jeffries Pryor
says
is that you should take a prior belief
about a system
the belief that is maximally uncertain
uncertain but that is also compatible
with your knowledge
so out of all priorities that are
compatible with what you know about the
system you would take the one that's
most uncertain
and this seems pretty intuitive right
so when you take Jeffrey's prior
what you what you get
is often a distribution that's in the
form of what people call a Gibbs measure
so it gives the measures or gives
distributions there of the form
exponential minus V
um so they're like proportional to
and V could be an arbitrary function so
if V just as an example if V were like a
parabola a quadratic function then the
associated uh Gibbs distribution is a is
the gaussian so we all know what
gaussians are right but we could be
pretty much anything if you take a v to
be like
x to the power 4 minus x to the power of
2 then V is kind of like a a camel about
upside down so you know it has like two
humps
and therefore the exponential minus V
distribution the Gibbs measure would be
like um a gaussian but with two humps
um so this gives measures they just
arrive they're just there like
everywhere and they they come up all the
time
um so one example one other example is
in statistical mechanics so let's say
you have a like a system of molecules
that just interact with each other and
these system of molecules they they
could also be subject to you know
thermal thermal fluctuations and and
whatnot
um this system is going to relax to what
people call a steady state often a
non-equilibrium steady state
these steady states which is kind of
like the
the end configuration of the system
is
um in general a gives measure
um so so yeah so now you can see that in
statistical mechanics and also in
statistics
gives measures comes up come up also in
you know basic inference
and um it's a very hard in general to
sample from a Gibbs measure I mean
there's ways to do it and and we're
gonna come back to it but you know we
need to solve this problem it's a very
important problem
and so
when you know the the most common way to
sew from this distribution is uh what's
called Mark of chain Monte Carlo
so the idea is to run a Markov chain so
to run like a stochastic process and you
could think of it as a
stimulating
um you know molecule that interact with
each other with some thermal
fluctuations and that are going to relax
to this gives distribution this steady
state that you originally specified
um so coming back to the original
examples the steady state could be like
a gaussian they want to sample from
um going back to the example of the desk
it could be the uniform Distribution on
the desk that we want to sample from it
could also be gives measure so we can
so once we know the distribution that we
want to assemble from
um we're gonna run we're gonna design a
stochastic process some kind of random
motion that's
who whose distribution is going to
converge to the Target distribution
so as you run the process
think of it as running you know
stimulating those molecules that
interact and that converge to your
target
um yeah so you're just gonna like
simulate that and once the your system
has converged to its steady state which
is the target distribution then each
movement on the steady state density is
going to give you a new sample
um
so so just for intuition let's come back
to the desk and say that we have you
know this uniform measure uniform
Distribution on the desk that we want to
sample from so we're gonna design like a
dynamic that moves you know randomly
around
and that's going to converge to the
uniform distribution which means that if
you run it long enough
it's just going to sample everywhere on
the desk and it's going to sample each
point equally often
and so you're just going to run this
Dynamic for a very long time
and and then you're going to collect the
samples
collect the samples and use them to
approximate the integral that you
started with
um so this is how sampling is done
now there's two uh there's yeah
basically one big question one big
outstanding question is how do you
choose this dynamic how do you choose
this random motion to converge uh to
your to your target distribution to
sample from the distribution
so given a target distribution there's
like a close form formulas for
all all the possible choices of
processes that you can use to sample
from them
so that's a closed problem and that's
also explained in the in the paper but
then out of all of these processes you
would like to know which one is going to
sample the most efficiently
and you also want to know
um and and the second of all
uh a lot of the analysis of stochastic
processes is done in continuous time so
you know that if you implement this
process
it's gonna it's gonna converge at this
rate to the Target distribution and so
the the faster it converges the better
um but it could be that when you
simulate this on a computer in a
computer you can only you know have like
discrete time steps or like discrete
operations in discrete time so you
cannot really simulate this dynamic in
continuous time
so every time you simulate it it's going
to introduce some error now it could be
that the thing that you simulate on your
computer actually goes a lot slower than
the than the original process that you
wanted to simulate so there's these two
uh questions how do you take a process
that you know samples very efficiently
converges very fast to your target
but in addition to that how do you
stimulate the process accurately on your
computer starts to retain all the
um all the important characteristics of
of that process
um
so there's many different criteria and
and this is what we what we discussed
essentially uh one method that's state
of the art or among the state of the art
is called hamiltonian Monte Carlo
now
um hamiltonian Monte Carlo without
getting into too much detail
um
it takes uh it has two advantages the
First Advantage is that it can be
analyzed
um using mathematical methods so you can
get guarantees based on your target
distribution you can get guarantees of
how fast you're going to converge how
accurate your samples are going to be
and so on
um it has also many other desirable
properties so one of them which we
discuss a lot in the paper is the
importance of being irreversible
so irreversible
means being irreversible means that
if you run the process forward in time
or if and so let's say let's say you run
the process forward in time for like 10
seconds let's say you run the process
backward in time so you kind of like
run the process backward and you just
like take a movie and play it backward
and look at how the process behaves
now a process is reversible if the
forward and the backward movies
are statistically in this
indistinguishable
um and a process is irreversible if if
if you run the time if you run time as
time goes forward if you run time
forward
it would look statistically different
from if you run the process backward
um
so so this there's some yeah I I think
that you can kind of like picture what
what irreversibility is now
irreversibility is crucial to to do
efficient sampling because if you're
reversible
um it means that you're gonna backtrack
very often
when you're sampling positions on the
decks on the desk say you're going to
start somewhere go somewhere else and
then there's a non-trivial chance a
significant chance that you're going to
come back to where you started so it's
going to be very slow to explore all the
desks and you know build skyscrapers
everywhere
um so so then sampling turns out to be
very slow now when you're irreversible
um there's way less chances that you
just come back to where you started so
you're gonna like explore the desk a lot
faster because you're not allowed to
come back to the same place so much
and so
you can assemble faster and it's going
to be much more efficient
um so it's actually by going from a
reversible process for sampling to an
irreversible process you can gain like
orders and Orders of magnitude
efficiency it's actually like pretty
pretty crazy
it's the hamiltonian Monte Carlo
as guarantees
is irreversible
it has other desirable properties
um and the main one is that you can
actually
stimulate it on your computer in a way
that the discretized version which you
actually simulate on the computer is
going to be very very
um very close
to
um to the true hamiltonian Monte Carlo
that you get you know by writing the
equation down
so these this is like why it's so big
and and you know why why people use it
um
so
yeah I think this is pretty much it oh
yeah so hamiltonian Monte Carlo has um
an accept rejects that
which is
so coming coming back to
um to when you simulate a process on
your computer every time you you know
discretize a process to introduce some
error now you want to make that
discretization error as small as
possible so that your so that the
process that you actually stimulate on
your computer is very close to to what
you want to simulate
um so hamiltonian Monte Carlo has
a very uh a step a step a very important
step called Metropolis Hastings
which which uh is gonna say
am I should I keep the sample or should
I you know drop this sample and go to
the next sample
and um
by by using Metropolis Hastings it's a
it's a very clever clever but also
simple procedure
uh by using Metropolis Hastings
you guarantee that the distribution that
you're gonna sample is exactly the same
that as the distribution that you want
to assemble so just to just to put in
other maybe uh simpler term simpler
terms
um so you have this process that you
want to simulate
this process is gonna assimilate it is
going to sample your target distribution
now it could be that when you discretize
the process because the discretized
process is different you're gonna
stumble from a different a slightly
different distribution Now by using
Metropolis Hastings you're gonna
guarantee that this distribution that
you sample from in practice is exactly
the same as what you really want to
sample from
and so that's very important because it
it just tells you that
um asymptotically
um as as the number of samples just Rose
to Infinity uh you're gonna recover
exactly what you wanted to recover which
is the high dimension integral
awesome I remember the Metropolis
Hastings and the Monte Carlo Markov
chains in phylogenetics
where you might have many many species
and many many locations in the genome
that you're doing phylogenetic inference
over and you just sample sample sample
and so all these techniques help
accelerate what's possible with any
given computational Hardware
so how would you bring this towards
adaptive agents are we thinking about
this sampling process as being Guided by
an Adaptive agent and or are we sampling
distributions
about an Adaptive agent
that that's you know a great question
and I think it sort of brings
us to the conclusion of this work is you
can so in order to have adaptive agents
and
to scale adaptive agents so so that
they're able to solve complex problems
and you're able to implement them with
like finite computational resources
one uh useful tool is sampling and we'll
see many different places where sampling
can be used and has been used in active
inference
um
but and that's basically what you said
sampling
is at the at the heart of at the heart
of sampling is you know choosing data
points intelligently
so as to approximate your your integral
or whatever it is that you want to do
with those samples
so you could think of
um
adaptive agents as solving the sampling
problem you could think
of an active inference agent when you
let's say there you have a problem of
sampling you could think of an agent an
active inference agent that's going to
choose oh I'm going to assemble here and
I'm going to sample here and I'm going
to sample here
so active inference agent in in the
proper sense of the word they do
sampling all the time
um the only I would say slight
difference with what we've just
discussed is that active inference
agents they sample observations so that
they're they comply with their
preferences
and the observations that also bring
them new information about the world
so the the objective that active
inference agents use to to select new
samples is the expected free energy so
typically
we select actions or or policies that
have the lowest expected free energy
which means that the resulting
observations will be
close to your preferences or goal and
also bring you new information about the
world
um
but you could also con conceivably think
of an agent as you know selecting
actions so that the resulting samples or
observations accurately sample
distribution
um
so how could sampling be used in the
context of active inference
and
adaptive agents and so this is actually
a great slide
um because so if you if you look at the
upper panel
is is what we what I just discussed so
in in the first equation uh that's up
there you see that the sequence of
actions that you choose in active
inference is the one that minimizes this
minus log P this distribution of our
action sequences
so this minus log p is actually the
expected free energy
so we choose action sequences that means
as you see on the equation just below
the expected free energy is a sum of
risk and ambiguity so you're going to
choose action sequences that minimize
risk but that also minimize ambiguity
about the world and in other words as
shown below you're going to choose
action sequences that maximize extrinsic
value so you could think of that as an
expected reward and intrinsic value so
that would be expected Information Gain
value that's intrinsic because you gain
information
um
so the really the the key here is that
this expected free energy it's given as
as it name suggests it's given by an
expectation
uh so you see this minus log p on the
left equals expectation of something now
when you have a very big generative
model or a very big world model
um which is going to be the case all the
time when you have like um
a real world application or a complex
application because the world around us
is so high dimensional so complex
um
well the expected for energy then is
going to be a high dimensional
expectation what is an expectation it's
an integral with respect to a
probability distribution
so
um the the point I want to get to is
that to do decision making
you need to evaluate the expected free
energy of different action sequences
and this expected free energy is an
expectation with respect to probability
distribution it's a very high
dimensional
integration problem and very high
dimensional integration expectation
and so how do you approximate that while
you use sampling and I think the the
first work that actually used that in
the first uh in the context of active
inference is the work by uh funtas at
all
uh 2020 of um
it I think it's called skating active
inference with Monte Carlo method
uh you have some tests with f o u
um
[Music]
yeah for you and
um yeah scheduling active inference when
Monte Carlo methods so this is what they
did they and and I think it was
published in Europe
so very big machine learning conference
and you know their observation was okay
well we have this
um active inference method which
theoretically
is very powerful I mean in the sense
that you have this expected free energy
objectives that puts a lot of known
constructs together
uh so you know the expected free energy
has shown in in figure three here puts
together this risk so this is the
Divergence between your predict the
distribution of where you're going to be
in the world and your target
distribution of where you want to be in
the world
and it has this ambiguity term as well
which has some nice links with them
phenomena in Psychology like the
streetlight effect
so when you minimize when you choose
actions that minimize ambiguity you can
recover phenomenology that's known in
Psychology like the street light effect
or the drunkard search
risk is also an objective that's used in
engineering
um
in in control as inference so you can
see it on on the left panel so there are
a few methods for you know doing
adaptive agents that use the skl term
one would be contrast inference which is
also known as maximum entropy
reinforcement learning and KL control
and also I think
although it needs to be investigated
further
um it hasn't been formally I think so
far but with the KL term there you can
recover uh predictions that are made by
prospect theory which is a big Theory
from the end of the 20th century about
decision making in human agents
um so this is I think um
worthwhile to look into further but um
I think there's some very clear links
between that theory and and this scale
term in the expected for energy anyway
um so you have this expected Community
objective that's very powerful has a lot
of puts a lot of things together so I
think theoretically it's very nice
um in in the
last line of the upper panel you can
also see that you can view expected PNG
as weighing expected reward and expect
the information gain so extreme deep
value intrinsic value and extrinsic
value it's used
um you know in expected utility Theory
based on decision Theory RL optimal
control so these are all like equivalent
names for maximizing this extrinsic
value
an intrinsic value expected Information
Gain it's also used in many different
places
and in for example in Bayesian
experimental design which is
um in statistics it was a seminal paper
by Lindy in 1956
and Lindley basically said okay well
suppose that you you can do two
experiments
um or many different experiments how how
should you choose between them what's
the best experiment that that you should
do and the answer that he came up with
is you should use uh you should do the
experiment that gives you the most
information about the world
and
so you have to keep in mind that in in
that paper there was no like extrinsic
goal it was not like we're gonna do an
experiment to you know solve this
problem or or achieve this results it
was only
um doing an experiment for the sake of
it and so he came to the conclusion that
the best experiment was the one that
maximized expected information game now
suppose that you have a goal in mind uh
Target
um the target result or or whatnot
then you would weigh reasonably I mean
one thing you could do is weigh the
expected Information Gain with your
expected reward or expected utility or
expected how close you're gonna get to
your goal and so this is exactly what
the expected free energy does it puts
these two uh things on the same footing
um
so
so you have this expected free energy
which is very nice and which is you know
uh what active inference brings to the
table
and what Fontes edel did in their paper
is okay well we have this cool method
active inference let's use it to solve
non-trivial machine learning slash
reinforcement learning problems
um and so when you when you actually
want to solve those problems you have
some high dimensional generative models
High dimensional State spaces that just
come up and you need sampling to
evaluate
um
to approximate the expected three
energies so this is what they did and
they also put together a lot of other
cool tricks based on neural networks and
so on
um so a very cool paper totally
recommend but I think the the point it
suggests and this is also the point that
we make although in a very different way
in this paper is that to actually do
decision making efficiently in practice
efficiently but also you want to do take
good decisions you actually need
sampling
and and this is not a new Point by the
way
um I think it's
many people would agree with this
um but I think the the active inference
approach is nice because you have this
um explicit characterization of expected
preenergy as an expectation of something
so it becomes pretty clear that you want
to do sampling because this is what the
sampling is made for
um
so I initially introduced sampling as
you know wanting to approximate
integrals but expectations are integrals
um so yeah sampling is really what you
want it just comes out like extremely
directly uh when you want to do these
kind of things
awesome thanks and one sensory example
of information driven sampling is the
icicade the movement of the eyes which
also has been modeled in many works from
the active inference perspective
and it's even below our level of
conscious awareness
with the eyes darting around to reduce
their uncertainty such that our visual
generative model can have high
resolution and color
throughout the visual field
even though that doesn't reflect the
anatomy of the retina which has a blind
spot and differential resolution and
color detection in the periphery so I
kind of see that as slam dunk evidence
that our visual experience and by
extension other sensory modalities
are coming from the generative model
they're not just received and processed
in an inward bound fashion
and that adaptive sampling is vital to
maintain the coherence of that
generative model
absolutely absolutely you want to do
adaptive sampling in order to
Reserve preserve the structure I mean
you have this beautiful structure in the
expected free energy
of expect Information Gain so let's say
we're just like wanting we're just like
looking at stuff so we don't have any
direct goal the expected energy reduces
to expect Information Gain or you know
approximates that and you just want to
sample you sampling is the key to
approximate you know this expected
Information Gain term while preserving
the statistics of the genitive model
so it's very um
you're very Central to scaling active
interference I wouldn't say I wouldn't
say it's Central to active inference
proper just the theory
because in the theory you get these
expectations and and you know how to
select actions but anytime you want to
scale active inference deploy active
inference to solve a problem you want to
I mean sampling is going to come into
play inevitably
um
and if
yeah and yeah I mean there's there's
other ways to to scale active inference
one other way could be
what's called amortizing amortization so
with deep neural networks so one thing
you could do is train a neural network
to predict the expected green energy
based on your genital model and near
sensory data uh but this amortization
procedure as does any training of neural
networks it's going to require a lot of
data so it's going to be slow it's not
something that you can deploy right away
um so this is a very nice way of I mean
amortization should is a very nice way
of doing things but it's not something
that you can use like the first time you
use active inference to solve a new task
so
um a nice way of of you know scaling
active inference and and it's not the
only way or it's not going to solve all
the problems but it would be to
um
use sampling to approximate the expected
for energy to make decisions in real
time and as you accumulate data then you
can train a neural network to predict
the expected free energy I think this is
exactly what funtas at all did in their
paper by the way so so if you're
interested make sure to check it out
figure three
it's something that one can just look at
for so long
because
the imperative what is being utilized in
action selection by an active inference
agent
is something like a generalization of
all the words that we see written lower
and unless we knew about that
generalization or that unified
imperative
it seems like these are quite literally
orthogonal or disparate from each other
I mean what could be more different than
maximum Information Gain oriented
strategies and maximum reward driven
strategies and sometimes to get both
those flavors in the same model people
might try to coerce one into the other
usually we see that in terms of a
novelty bonus or an exploratory impulse
bolted on to a reward or a pragmatic
value driven agent and so once you start
modifying the models and just adding in
these arbitrarily constructed components
you may get adaptive Behavior it's never
been a claim in the active space that
other models don't have efficacy
rather that by thinking about all of
these special cases
as being
situationally arising from a more
General imperative with expected free
energy for future oriented policy
selection
we might gain the ability to do what
what will we gain
conceptually or or in practice
by taking situations where today people
are using maybe just one of these terms
as an imperative for what
their models are doing and what do we
gain or what might we expect
from potentially generalizing those
imperatives
you know that's um that's a brilliant
and very difficult question
um it's also a question that I would say
everybody in active inference gets asked
at some point
um because
people
um let's say people doing reinforcement
learning they they use many different
objectives that would perhaps be
tailored to solving one particular task
or a different task and they would
um have these um ad hoc novelty bonuses
that would work very well in certain
tasks and
so it's a it's a different approach
um the the this this approach that I was
just mentioning with reinforcement
learning it tends to be
um it's much more bottom up it's it's
like we we want to have an agent that
still that solves this problem makes
this work and so on so we're gonna you
know build uh start building and and
test it until it works
uh the active inference approach is top
down
um so it's it you know it starts from
the community principle and it's very
theoretical and the approach is like
okay well let's model how an agent
interacts with its environment the most
generic kind of agent and let's impose
constraints that an agent has to satisfy
so the
um the basic constraints that we have in
this paper is that you have three sets
of variables yeah you have variables in
the external world that you cannot
directly have access to
so this would be
um maybe the temperature in the room
um then you have sensory variables or
observations so by the way the the
environmental variables that are denoted
as s uh the sensory observations or the
observation or the observations that are
denoted as o so this is what's what
belongs to the world
and you have direct access to
this would be like your Sensations what
you see and so on and then you have the
actions denoted in the paper by a which
is uh basically what you can do and I
mean the different things the different
options that you can choose from at any
point in time and this is what will
enable you to influence the world as and
influence your observations oh
so we start from a very generic model of
an agent and how it interacts with the
world these three sets of variables that
evolve in time
and
just by adding a few other
um
I would say constraints that agents uh
satisfied or intelligent agents
hopefully satisfied you get that these
agents
um can be described as minimizing as
taking decisions that minimize the
expected free energy so the expected
free energy just comes up from this
general theory of how agents behave
um
so
to answer your question what what does
this actually bring in practice well
first of all
um
there's many methods out there that are
similar to active inference
in some cases they're
almost the same the the first different
is
which is not necessarily an advantage of
a disadvantage but it's the approach
these other methods that you see out
there that come very close to active
inference they have been designed from a
bottom up
approach of like we want to model the
system or we want to solve this task so
we're going to add all the components
that are needed until our agent does
what we want it to do and it turns out
that sometimes all these ingredients
turn out to be exactly what we get in
active inference or very similar
um
other times uh maybe the task would be
simpler and you would get less
ingredients
the disadvantage of that I would say is
that it can turn out to be very messy so
you get a new task or a new thing to
model maybe a new paradigm that some
subject would do and you end up using a
very different model
a very different objective to describe
the behavior at hand so it's not very um
you know it's harder to have like a
unified perspective of what's going on
active inference the I would say the key
the key contribution is that you get
this unified perspective from it you get
this objective that puts together a lot
of other constructs that we that we know
and love and put them together and you
know that with this objective you can do
a lot of things
which is for example decision making
that way is exploration and exploitation
now there's there are some challenges
with active inference and anybody using
active reference would be familiar with
them the first one is the scaling up
because you have this approach item
inference which is so complex in a way I
mean you need to have a giant model of
the world
you need to have uh to be able to
compute all these expectations now first
of all you need to be able to compute
all these posterior distributions using
Bayes rule or variational inference
then once you have those posterior or
approximate posterior distributions
based on your high dimensional model of
the world then you need to compute some
expectations
very high dimensional expectations using
sampling or whatnot to then get the
expected free energy so the expected for
energy doesn't come up for free it's
actually a very
um I would say it's quite sufficient
it's a quite sophisticated thing I mean
it puts all these things together but it
doesn't come for free it's um
it's hard to implement on on a practical
problem that's you know non-trivial
beyond to assimilations and people have
done it but it's a challenge
um
so the problem the problem that active
inference has is okay well we have this
Knight Theory we have this very nice
objective that theoretically works very
well and theoretically it's it's like or
it's similar to what you would like to
have for any kind of
um
yeah any kind of agenda
but we need to find ways of scaling this
up
and and so here comes here comes like
kind of like the beauty of of this is
that in scaling up active inference
you're gonna use sampling you're gonna
use techniques from optimization from
inference
um and so you're gonna get something
that's slightly different from the
active reference scheme that you started
with
so you had this active inference scheme
proper which was in the picture
um
in in the previous slide
and um
and so you know this is active inference
as as you would like to implement it if
you could but but because the problem is
complicated and you have a high
dimensional State space and so on you
have many things that are
computationally intensive you're going
to use sampling you're going to use
optimization you're going to use
inference and so you're gonna get
something uh an active inference
algorithm and that scales but that's
slightly different from what you started
because it has all these other steps
now in doing so in doing so the active
influence agent becomes engineered
so it becomes closer to
um
this these uh reinforcement learning and
bottom-up agents that are built in a
bottom-up way to solve certain tasks you
know because you want to engineer the
active reference algorithm to be able to
work to solve a certain problem to to
scale it in a certain way
so in doing so active Enterprise becomes
closer to reinforcement learning now
conversely
um in reinforcement learning
people the the amount of compute is
is increasing
um people
want to you know build reinforcement
learning agents that are increasingly
learn in a unsupervised manner just
because this scales better I mean you
can't
um you can't always you know design all
the
um all the components of your
reinforcement learning agent to solve
any single tax it's just too impractical
especially when
uh ties become more and more complicated
uh you just would like General solutions
that you know are gonna work
um and are going to handle a lot of
different types of situations
so reinforcement learning is adding or
subtracting ingredients to their
algorithms their all these algorithms
are evolving but in in some sense you
can see this is debatable I suppose but
you can see a general tendency towards
uh moving to World models and generated
models moving to
intrinsic motivation which is another
word for expected Information Gain or or
variance thereof
and an intrinsic motivation or intrinsic
value that's added onto extrinsic value
which is your expected reward so
you see many I mean I think we're seeing
reinforcement learning evolving the
direction also that is closer to active
inference because
um
yeah because everybody wants algorithms
that little different tasks
um and and not to have to change the
algorithms for for you know uh changing
environments and so on
um so in my view even though we started
with two different approaches a
bottom-up approach and a top-down
approach
these are converging
now the
to come back to the contribution of
active inference
um the so if if one reads through the
paper and what looks at the derivation
of active inference
the point is that it's very agnostic
it's agnostic to the environment that
we're in it's an agnostic to many things
so it's very very general
and so
if you take many practical reinforcement
learning agents
um you will see that they interact with
their environment in a way that's
compatible with the assumptions of the
free energy principle
in other words
um
the
uh reinforcement learning agents can be
recast as specific active inference
agents with specific giant models
so this is really the key thing it's
this unifying
perspective I'm not saying it unifies
everything
but I'm saying that many different
reinforcement learning algorithms can be
recast as active inference agents
and so this is not to say that the
active inference implementation of those
reinforcement algorithms is going to be
better
but it's more like um it's more like a
theoretical contribution of like
this set of equations given by the
expected free energy is a complete
recipe for almost complete recipe to
generate adaptive agents so in some
sense you don't have to go any further
than that
and so you can view all these
reinforcement learning algorithms that
comply with the assumptions so there can
be recast as active reference algorithms
as ways of scaling and making of scaling
active inference and making active
inference work
so it's not like
um I don't see any you know
um
any kind of conflict between active
influence and reinforcement learning
makes more like the reinforcement
learning algorithms that work well and
that can be recast as active inference
algorithms and there are many
I mean there I would say more than more
algorithms that can be recast that are
greater than that cannot
when you look at the assumptions of the
free energy principle that are super
generic
so you can view all these algorithms as
specific implementations of active
inference in a way that active
references meant to scale well
so this is kind of like
um this thing and so
I think ultimately again these two
fields are going to converge
but I do not see any tension between
them it's more like the tools from one
can be used in the other and
and um and yeah I see I mean I see great
work going forward and this is kind of
like what we want to do with this paper
you know put this
um active inference where where it comes
from very succinctly
and also
um you know make it accessible for
people who don't know the jargon from
the 300 principle and active reference
community and yeah see see you uh I mean
the exciting developments that that will
follow
wow great comments two things that that
reflects to me the constraints that you
mentioned which we sometimes call the
particular partition essentially
cleaving the particle which you show in
um figure
two
cleaving the particle
from the environment this is something
that's widely applied in agent-based
modeling just anytime you're talking
about some field of action and a player
where basically at least qualitatively
within the space of partitioning Agents
from environments and then further
saying well there's no Edge between the
internal and the external state so
there's no telepathy and there's no
telekinesis
and incoming information we're going to
call sense outgoing we're going to call
Action that qualitatively and formally
is basically consistent with almost any
cybernetic formulation of adaptive
action so the constraints are really
quite minimal and seemingly being
generalized year after year with the
work so many colleagues are involved in
so the constraints are not
onerous
and I think it's a really interesting
question which reinforcement learnings
are compatible and then coming from the
other side in in a lot of active
modeling contexts we find ourselves
sometimes proposing like auxiliary
variables like let's just do a parameter
sweep over this and then we'll look back
to the textbook or to the paper we think
well where was that in expected free
energy we just proposed this random
thing where was that in the equation or
we'll look at step-by-step guide to
active inference where it's all written
in terms of matrices it's all very
read it like a sentence and all of a
sudden it's like wait a could be a
neural network it doesn't just have to
be a matrix so it's kind of like we we
bring in
these methods and ingredients that are
being used widely empirically
and these are the two approaches do we
build the bottom-up Mosaic of approaches
stopping when it works
and or do we start with this most
General agent-based cybernetic
formulation
and then
kind of build the castle in the sky
and meet in the middle again with
something that works it's just
incredibly laid out
and this paper is at that saddle point
because it has one hand
or antenna or whatever in this smooth
information geometry
conceptual area
but the motivator of all of the
conceptual moves that are made which
honestly are extensive like page after
page it was just like where's it going
it's going somewhere that can be
simulated on everyday Hardware
so many of the moves were about
reshaping or reframing
what was to be done in a way that could
be simulated
and so those two paths are connecting
and like you said there's not
necessarily
attention
but it'll be quite interesting to see
how this develops
on the
Theory practice and social Frontiers
as more and more of these threads start
to combine
yeah I agree
I think it's um
particularly beautiful when you know
Theory meets practice
um you oftentimes have you know practice
that works but you have no Theory
or you have a theory that's beautiful
but that doesn't work in practice and
you know this just happens all the time
um typically you would have practice
that works and then you would try to
build a theory out of it but then often
the theory turns out to be too hard so
you know make some extra assumptions and
so on you end up with a theory but the
theory turns out to be quite removed
from the practice so you cannot get that
Gap
um so it's very beautiful and quite
unique and also quite rare when the
theory meets The Practice
when and I would say when the theory
meets the practice and in particular
means the state of the art when then you
kind of have a complete Theory
um so what we wanted to do in this paper
is review these different fields in a
way that
um we could show how far we how far the
community uh has gone between
me making a theory that meets the state
of the art and and every every section
was started with theoretical
configuration theoretical considerations
about what should be
when you need to solve a particular
problem let's say adaptive agents or
or sampling or or optimization and then
from there and from logical steps about
okay well it should be like this and not
like that because there's this
you know whatever kind of geometric
argument or or other arguments and and
so from there logically
arriving at
state-of-the-art methods that are used
in practice
um the the other kind of like sequence
of logical steps was okay well we're
gonna start with optimization
which is in my view at the root of
everything
um so sampling it could be about
optimizing samples such to obtain the
best approximation interior integral
inferences about optimizing beliefs and
decision making it's about optimizing
decisions based on their contractual
consequences so we started off with
optimization because it's the simplest
thing both conceptually and also in
terms of use case
you need optimization to do everything
else
um we then went to sampling and to
inference and finally to decision making
because it just brings all these three
ingredients together we didn't go as far
as showing okay well this is how you
should scale active inference in order
to solve all the problems in the world
because this just hasn't been done right
but we listed a few ingredients that
have gone into the literature and also a
few ingredients that this perspective
offers to you know how to scale active
inference and make it more effective so
it's actually future work and an open
problem to you know use the techniques
that have been developed in the sampling
section and the sampling literature to
make actually inference even more
scalable and same with optimization and
same with inference so there's many
things
many things that have been put forward
in this article and also elsewhere
that can be used to
you know scale active influence but at
least yeah the goal was to be as
comprehensive as possible without
sacrificing too much of actually
understanding what's really going on
and
um show how the theory meets the
practice throughout and really where
where the field stands
so one one kind of reflection on this
again is um
if we start with reward as our basal
imperative pragmatism I mean after all
don't we want to get things done achieve
results in the world realize our
preferences we start with
pragmatism and then it is
empirically ad hoc how people introduce
these novelty bonus or intrinsic
motivations
in contrast
we can start with this Information Gain
approach and then the thumb is put on
the scale
to bring more and more emphasis onto the
alignment with preference
so it's
like
two roads two paths
and
maybe this is our bias or corner of the
information space that starting with a
broader epistemic imperative
allows the careful introduction of
pragmatic value
whereas a pragmatic Foundation
that uh
it's hard to then recast
epistemic value in terms of pragmatic
value that's kind of like the question
of valuing basic research and the
approach taken here is
develop an imperative that can look
entirely like one or the other or
mixtures
but what's always so perplexing is that
it has this extrinsic and intrinsic
value
phrasing
but there are other ways to decompose
the function
so even intrinsic and extrinsic value
are not necessarily
the ingredients that were put in it's
more like they were two ingredients that
were split out
of something else that is much more
integrated
it wasn't like the free energy was
constructed
by composition
of
any given decomposition of which there
are multiple for variational free energy
and expected free energy
and so then a question that I've often
wondered is there might be two policies
that are very close or have essentially
identical expected free energy
but they could be radically different
for example one could be
uh having a good expected free energy
because it realizes a lot of preferences
another might because it
provides a lot of Information Gain
so
is it really
as simple
asterisk asterisk asterisk
as a unified imperative
or how do we
make sense of the fact that one value
could rank policies
that might have for example extremely
different danger profiles or envelopes
of outcomes how can that
seemingly
multi-dimensional space be projected
into
essentially a ranking
yeah it's um
it's a complicated question I would say
the I mean as we can see the expected
free energy does this in some way it
provides an answer to this question
based on your preferences and how much
you would gain by of the by observing
this new data how much information you
would gain
you can put these two things on the same
footing this is what expected per energy
does and it gives you a ranking
um you're right to say that
you're right to say that two very
different courses of action could have
the same expected free energy
um and so how do you choose between them
well
the the standard formulation that you
would see in textbooks or papers has
okay well G of action sequence equals
this and G of equity sequence equals
that so these two action sequences are
the same G and you don't know what to do
but here
um the this theoretical development in
this paper makes it very clear that the
expected PNG is a minus log probability
and this is why um so to make it more
transparent instead of using the letter
G that's commonly used in the literature
we used
uh we kept the minus log P throughout so
we never use the letter G
and so the expected free energy is this
minus log P of action sequence
and so it says okay well if two action
sequences have the same expected for
energy well then you have let's say you
just have two of them with the same
expected strategy the lowest one well
then you choose probabilistically like
half of the time you choose one and half
of the time reduce the other
if it's a even a bit more complicated
because if you since it's a minus sloppy
you could have like um an action
sequence with a very high
uh expected free energy and so this
means that you can still take it but you
would take it like not very often so you
have an exponentially low chance of
taking that action sequence so it's it's
a probabilistic description it doesn't
say
um it says that the most likely action
sequence would be the argument the
minimum of the expected free energy so
this is like the Top Line in in the
figure and so if you have two most
likely action sequences well then you
choose like half of the time you choose
one half of the time you use the other
but then in general if you didn't want
to simulate the most likely action
sequence then you choose
probabilistically between all of them
and the the action sequences that have
the lowest expected friendly has an
exponentially higher chance of being
selected
and the others don't
that so there's a sorry one last thing
so there's another very nice perspective
is that
the probability of our action sequences
so these P of a greater than equal to T
is then the exponential
of minus the expected free energy
because if you take exponential minus of
what you get in the equality on on the
left
then you recover this probability
distribution over action sequences so
this variety of this region of our
action sequences is exponential minus
expected PNG exponential minus what's in
there and we saw before that gives
measures they arise everywhere and so
this is an example of a Gibbs measure
you have exponential minus something
you basically based on the formalism of
the free energy principle
it comes up that the distrib the
probability distribution of our actions
is a Gibbs measure
it it is uh the Gibbs measure where
what's inside is the expected free
energy
so yeah it's kind of like a full circle
thing and and this is basically
this sort of like
connections they just happen all the
time when we were writing this paper and
discussing because this so many things
that just
uh there's so many crossovers at so many
different levels like on the uh sort of
like object level that you're studying
but also on the methodological level
like methodologies that are used in some
field are used in a different field to
do something else
so there's so many Crossovers and so
this is
um I would say an interesting example of
why
you know gives measures gives
distribution and they just arise
everywhere and they arise in active
inference and
as we saw before they're hard to sample
from so if you wanted to
so let's say you have your Gibbs
distribution that says okay well this is
my distribution of our action sequences
that I get from the expected free energy
now you have two choices either you
sample from it do you sample like um
um yeah an average I would say not a
typical a typical action sequence or you
could optimize this distribution or
optimize the expected for energy to
sample the most likely action sequence
in in the two cases after you've done
your planning with the expected PNG you
have a choice between sampling and
optimization
so you kind of go back full circle of
like
um if I want to select my action in the
end I had to select the most likely
action by optimizing the expected PNG
or the Gibbs measure uh this I mean by
optimizing this minus log B by taking
the the yeah the action sequence with
the minimal expected Community or I have
my gives measured and it will sample
from it to like get a typical action
sequence
so it's all like super interrelated
very interesting
in the par at all textbook from 2022
that dialectic is mapped onto the
mammalian nervous system
where policies can be selected by
essentially passing through habit
proportionally or
expected free energy can be applied to
sharpen or optimize the posterior on
action
and um
does this influence how you select micro
meso or macro actions
um you do you mean like
for a human being like actions at the
cellular level actions and the global
level or or is it something different
like at the personal
grasping a coffee cup at the micro
larger scale decisions attention
allocation communication emissions
yeah I think
um
I think all all of these things are I
mean can be formulated in in this
treatment so for example attention would
be
where you choose to place your focus or
your mental eye so to speak
um so that's an internal action it could
be unconscious it could be undirected
but it's still happening
um I'm not an expert but there's a lot
of talking
Consciousness research of like
you being conscious I mean there's some
there's a very low amount of process
that our conscious
and these change according to where your
inner eye or your conscious eye whatever
you want to call it like moves
um this could be thought of an mental
mental action or an interaction that you
may or may not control but still in
action
um so all these
all other actions whether it is planning
at the short time scale taking a coffee
cup standing uh or planning
at the longer time scale like what am I
gonna do after my PhD and so on
um all of these things are actions
um so typically and as as you know of
course we we model that by using
hierarchical models where you have
um
different levels in your giant models so
uh in in your model of the world and and
the higher levels that are like more
represent more abstract representations
more and and also longer time scales
um so it could be
let's say
um and at some higher level I'm gonna
take the plane to to go to Amsterdam for
example and at the lower level okay well
once in Amsterdam I'm gonna read this
this and this it's like
um this action at the higher level of
taking the plane predates everything
that you're going to do at low level
and so
factorizing these different decisions
into different levels of a of a model
allow you to be computationally I mean
practical when
um a practically implementable when you
make those decisions and presumably this
is why
we do in our everyday life factorize
decisions and representations into low
level and and high level things
um the beauty of the of the French
principle and of the treatment here
um but but the treatment here is again
just the free energy principle in in its
most Bare Bones and and general form is
that
um
the expected free energy is formulated
for any kind of genetic model
the genitive models that you have in in
the figure on the on the bottom right
there they they could be arbitrary so
you could use
this form of expected granity for
hierarchical giant models that have all
these like high level low-level
decisions and representations
um but you could also use it for any
other kind of genetic model World models
the only difference is that with some
World models it would be very hard to
implement this in practice
um and with other world models and in
particular those that are highly
factorized and distributed like
hierarchical models like the wounds we
we just talked about with these it would
typically be much simpler to
um take decisions and minimize expected
free energy
um in when it comes to like practical
computation just because when you have
factorized representations things just
um computations just factor out a lot
and it's just like way simpler too
to to do but the formulation here is
like entirely generic and it could apply
to
um all kinds of models and all kinds of
situations
very interesting well
in our last little segment on the dot
one
let's hear your
perspective or overview on the roadmap
just walk through what the sections are
and you mentioned some related topics
but what do the subjects broadly cover
why are they structured in that order
right
um so the well first of all the the
introduction it just puts like
everything in context
um the
kind of the the conducting line or or
one of the common points between all of
these sections is that there's a lot of
geometry
um so this was not purely you know uh
because the the journal is like the
handbook of Statistics it was called
geometry and statistics so this is not
just for that but it's because geometry
just comes up naturally you know in all
these places
um so this is what we explained in the
introduction like the
um how geometry comes up the different
branches that geometry of geometry that
come up in in this different fields and
and how they're interrelated and so just
from there you kind of get a picture on
of okay well this Branch let's say
Simplex geometry for example
um it comes up in accelerated
optimization and it also comes up in
sampling
and so you can also already see from
there like
what is going to be discussed of course
but also like which branches geometry of
geometry occur where and what what kind
of like parallels there there are
already
um so going from
the introduction to accelerated
optimization so optimization it's a
conceptually it's a very simple thing
it's like okay we have a function uh so
coming back to let's say that like the
state space come back to where we start
with and you have a function uh and a
landscape over it let's say like a
mountain
um
and so the goal is to find like the
minimum of of the mountain that go from
where you start to the minimum there's
so many different ways of solving this
problem
um practically speaking the the main
challenge of course is that you don't
know you cannot see
anywhere else except where you where you
have been
um so you start somewhere and you're
completely blind
and you need to find the minimum so how
do you do that
um there's so many ways uh so many
approaches to optimization I mean it's a
whole field and it's uh in my opinion a
very messy one
and this is understandable because at
this um the no freelance theorems that
are very well known uh that say that
under some hypotheses
um to ways of doing optimization will be
heading the same on average if you if
you um test them again all all possible
sorts of problems
um so this is to say that if you have a
given problem
then you need to give then the
optimization methods that will work well
are those that implicitly use the prior
information that you have about the
problem
in other words there's no
uh according to the ethereums there's no
optimization method that will you know
beat everything
it just doesn't exist because they're
all on average the same but this is not
to say that you cannot make any you know
practical meaningful steps by doing
optimization
because
um not all optimization problems are
you know the optimization problems that
we have in life they're not completely
random they're not completely random
Landscapes that we need to optimize but
they actually have some structure so we
can actually explore that in algorithms
and have things that just behave that
just work a lot better for the type of
problems that we're interested in than
others so this is what
um kind of like the starting point for
all optimization so the the the type of
optimization that we considered here is
optimization of smooth functions
um this is already like um a big
restriction there's so so many methods
that are designed to optimize functions
that are rugged
or non-smooth or have discontinuate
these and so on
um when when you actually get rugged or
discontinuous Landscapes it's a whole
different problem here we've chose to
focus on
smooth functions
and uh so the idea
is that well so you have a smooth
landscape you want to find the minimum
and one way to to do so and to do so
well is through the use of a tool called
geometric integration
um so I'll walk through the main ideas
of of this section
the the idea first of all is that
um you may design a method that
theoretically works very well
but when you implement it in practice on
your computer your discretization errors
uh because you you can only implement it
in discrete time
uh there what you actually end up
implementing ends up deferring
significantly from what you initially
wanted to implement
this is a problem that we discussed
previously in sampling and it just comes
up everywhere in Applied Mathematics and
numerical mathematics the fact that you
can only do discrete computations on
your computer is a Loom and a big
limitation and it's something that needs
to be looked into its maybe even the
most important thing and needs to be
looked into when building a numerical
method you want the numerical you want
to be able to
Implement numerical methods that are
very close from what you
from what you theoretically would like
to implement
so typically you would have some
theoretical algorithm that would have
some convergence guarantees or
performance guarantees and so we you
would like to a way to implement it on
your computer so as to preserve those
guarantees
um and this turns out to be very hard in
general
the one way one way to do it
um I would say the maybe the most
powerful way out there to to do this is
through
um procedures from the field of
geometric integration
and and so geometric integration in uh
is a set of techniques that allow you
under certain conditions to
discretize your theoretical dynamic or
theoretical optimization procedure or
like dynamical system
into
um and and you know make it into an
algorithm that you can practically
Implement on a computer
and that's going to respect the
performance
guarantees that you already have
um so now the the tricky part geometric
integration is based on Geometry so you
need to find
um it's not as simple as like okay well
um I have my my landscape my function
landscape and I'd like to just go down
and find the minimum one way to do that
is just by you know doing like gradient
descent and continuous time and you know
that that's gonna like go down until it
reaches a local minimum at the very
least so it's not too bad
if we were to implement gradient descent
and numerically wouldn't be exactly the
same
as like the continuous time Dynamic it
could be that actually by implementing
gradient descent numerically you get all
sorts of like
uh numerical problems or or whatnot
um maybe grain and scent it's so simple
it's not it's not actually a good
example but the the point I want to make
is that
um it's not as simple as like okay well
I have this Dynamic that works really
well and that gets to the minimum
and I know that it's going to get to the
minimum this fast
um and so geometric integration will
give me will give me an algorithm that
I can Implement on my computer and
that's going to get to the minimum this
fast as well it's not as simple as this
geometric integration works by
preserving geometric structures in the
dynamic that that you started with
so in order to be able to apply
geometric integration to have algorithms
that work for optimization you need to
design
A dynamical system that converges to the
minimum and that has some geometric
some important geometric features that
can be preserved in this way
and so this is basically the goal of the
whole section and it goes into into the
following steps
um
so one
thing that can be
um
you know discretized or implemented on a
computer in a way that is close to the
true dynamical system is what's called
hamiltonian flows so if you specify a
hamiltonian which is a kinetic energy
and potential energy then you get the
Hamilton Jacobi equations of motion
that gives you the behavior of the
system that has the prescribed
hamiltonian
so if you've for those who've taken a
course in physics you
probably know or or may have seen that
all of the Newtonian mechanics can be
reformulated as hamiltonian mechanics so
all that can be described as with
Newton's lowers the Newton Laws of
Motion can be described to through
hamiltonian mechanics so it's a very
general
framework or very general way to look at
physics
um
and so because it's such a general point
of view on physics and such a and this
hamiltonians they come up everywhere
this mixture of kinetic and potential
energy to continuously summarize the
behavior of the system
because they occur so much they have
been studied extensively
and it turns out that hamiltonians and
specifically the motion they entail so
the Hamilton Jacobi equations of motion
they can be
discretized or implemented accurately on
a computer
using symplectic integration which is a
part of geometric integration
so in
in short you can use simpletic
integration to accurately simulate a
hamiltonian dynamical system
now the problem is
um
these Dynamics are conservative so they
preserve the hamiltonian so if
if you're at some point in state space
with like a certain
kinetic energy potential energy and you
run the dynamic forward uh your overall
energy is not going to change so that's
standard physics energy is always
conserved uh when there's no friction so
in um so all all kind of like
IDEAL Physical systems with like no
friction no uh the the energy is
conserved so when you're gonna run this
simplexic optimization scheme to
simulate these Hamilton Jacobi equations
of motion the energy is going to be
conserved now we're in trouble if we
want to do an optimization because in
optimization if you think of the
function as the energy
uh you want to dissipate energy as much
as possible to reach the minimum so you
want to lose energy
um so what the what the section does so
this section by the way is a review of
more technical papers
what these papers do it's a very clever
trick is they say okay well we want to
minimize a function
we're going to say the function is a
potential energy and so we're going to
add a kinetic energy on top of that
together hamiltonian
and
so now this hamiltonian we could
stimulate it through
um
synthetic integration but actually if we
did we wouldn't dissipate the function
so now
um
what the what the section does is it
introduces like a
a higher dimensional State space
with the hamiltonian that if you if you
simulate those Dynamics it actually
optimizes the function
so this is like
um so this is what was a convoluted way
to say it reformulates optimization
as a conservative system with a
different hamiltonian and so by
um and
because we know how to simulate Dynamics
with hamiltonian so well a good way of
doing optimization is by finding a
hamiltonian that will so that when you
discretize it you get the optimization
process that you wanted
and so if you do that you get a
numerical method that's stable that
works well that has good convergence
guarantees and it turns out uh the
numerical methods that are developed
they work for optimization on any kind
of smooth manifold for functions and any
smooth functions on any smooth manifold
they work well they're generalized
gradient descent in the sense that you
recover great innocent in a certain
limit
and they can be seen as accelerated
because they have this notion of
acceleration in a sense that if you if
you
um let's say the function that you want
to optimize is like a hill and you want
to go down
if you just did greater in Ascent you're
like blindingly going down at the same
speed or or your speed is like
proportional to the slope of the
of the landscape but when you actually
let a robot a ball rolling down this is
not really what happens the ball is
going to roll faster and faster and it's
going to accelerate it's going to go
down it's going to overshoot the minimum
and then it's going to like oscillate
until it converges to a minimum
and so these are the kind of
optimization methods that are developed
here there
optimization methods that are
accelerated in a physical sense that has
a physical sense acceleration a physical
meaning
because they're going to accelerate as
they go down overshoot and then
stabilize
so this is the whole point of um of this
section now briefly because I think
we're running out of time but we can of
course revisit these sections later
um seeing them in the third section we
have sampling so we talked extensively
about sampling the
um sampling as we discussed can be seen
as an optimization of probability
distributions so we have
um we have this distribution that we
have one assemble from and we just run a
run a process That Is Random so it can
be described by its own distribution we
want the process to converge as fast as
possible to the Target
so you want the distribution of the
process to
you know
converge as fast as possible to the
Target distribution
so in a way that can be seen as I guess
complicated for for many people I think
it's pretty abstract
um but it's been known for a long time
that you know you can reformulate
sampling as just optimization of
distributions
um
now it turns out that when you use the
The Accelerated optimization method of
the second section
to
um to um to sampling so when you use
when you do accelerated optimization on
the space of probability distributions
in order to fill the sampling problem
you get a process that's called under
damp logical Dynamics so if you solve
that process
you're basically gonna get a good
samples very good samples of your target
distribution
because that process can be seen as
doing an accelerated optimization on the
space of probability distributions in
other words the distribution describing
the process is going to accelerate
towards the target so you're gonna like
get there very fast and your symbols are
going to be very good
um
so this is Missy
this is 2.6
where where this is kind of derived in
3.1 we basically talk about the
um
the good properties of Samplers in
general so sampling is not like a
complete field but there's a lot of work
showing that certain processes have I
mean certain characteristics of
processes make them better Samplers and
others make them worse
um so this is what we discuss and then
in 3.2 we put this all together in
hamiltonian Monte Carlo which is
the state-of-the-art method for sampling
um where where
um
so hamiltonian Monte Carlo is a way of
using
if you if you use simplexic integration
on under down below Dynamics which is
your accelerated sampling method that
you cannot stimulate directly again you
get the same problem if you use
sympathetic integration to simulate that
then you get hamiltonian Monte Carlo so
hamiltonian Monte Carlo is a practical
way of doing accelerated sampling that's
based on ideas of simplexic integration
um now very briefly
so the section 4 is on inference
so inference the inference in its most
general form is vibrational inference so
what we typically
um
do know and love from from active
inference and it's I have
um a Target probability distribution
that I'm not able to compute directly so
I'm going to approximate it as best as I
can
now um these
distributions they're often used to
compute expectations or in other words
in statistics and machine learning we
often you we often need to compute
expectations with respect to some
probability distribution
what this section does is it derives a
whole bunch of
divergences uh like The Kill Divergence
I mean the kill Divergence is not
discussed so much in this section I I'll
explain why
uh but it it derives a whole bunch of
divergences that can be used to you know
approximate this unknown distribution
with some other distributions that are
retractable
um so
to like put in a different way you have
this uh abstract variational inference
problem where you have this target
distribution
and then you have this family of
distributions that you know and you want
to select
um the distribution in your family that
best approximates your target
distribution
now um
you in order to do this you first need
to derive a measure of similarity
between distributions to know okay well
what what is the best distribution like
how can you quantify being the best
distribution being the best
approximation to your target
distribution and to do that you need to
specify your Divergence like the care
Divergence
the the
um the problem is the care Divergence is
not always uh practically applicable
uh one example is when the target
distribution is just given by samples
so maybe you don't even know the target
distribution like it maybe it's a
gaussian but you don't know it you just
have samples from the gaussian so you
kind of just have like a histogram
and you need to best approximate the
histogram
with the distribution in some family so
when you have a problem like this with
which just happens all the time you
cannot use the KL lab version so you
need to think about other divergences
and so when this section does is
deriving other classes of divergences
that are more generally applicable than
the kale Divergence
and they have also some very nice
properties and then showing okay well
how is it that I can minimize these
divergences to solving variation
reinference problem
um so I think there's a
lot of things to be done there in the
sense that in active inference we always
use the KL Divergence to
um to you know uh to do variation or
inference and minimize free energy and
it this scale Divergence is available
because we typically have
um alternative models that are nice and
that are expressed are graphical models
um
but there's this whole other
plethora of
divergences and algorithms to minimize
the divergences that's out there and it
could be the case that there's you know
very interesting recipes and methods
that can be either brought back to the
KL case that that we use or just used
all together in our setting
um
in particular
when for example let's say that we
wanted to you know approximate the
expected free energy in active inference
um the expected free energy is an
expectation and we want to approximate
that expectation
it could be the case
uh well I think I think these methods
there are like summarized in section
four could be very
useful because they they basically
develop divergences that quantify how
far the expectations are going to be if
you choose this a different distribution
so it's all like very natural
um in that computational sense
and then finally
adaptivations through active inference
well I think we've discussed that
already extensively but I won't boil it
more today and we can come back to it
next time
thanks a lot for that overview that was
very powerful
incredible dot one
very informative
looking forward to starting with some
questions from the live chat and
people's comments on the video between
now and next week if anybody else of
your colleagues or anyone in The
Institute wants to join
we'll be here next week for
52.2 so thank you Lance for the time
really appreciate it
thanks Daniel
farewell
see you next week bye
is it going to be the same